[Music]
I hope you can see this picture what
does this handle look
like can you all see can you all imagine
so please imagine for example a surface
like this a very smooth surface like
this and what this handle does is on
this surface I'm going
to make a hole
here make a hole here and this hole
around this hole I'm going to attach a
tube that comes out and then comes down
on the other hole and closes both holes
do you see what I'm doing yeah by doing
so I've closed both holes and I've
obtained a closed surface and that
that's one
handle in particular if you have just a
sphere to begin with and then I drilled
those holes and then Clos those holes by
attaching handle well it's something
that you can probably carry around yeah
but topologically it's the same thing as
a
Taurus okay in this case this is fat
this is thin but you know if you just
rearrange the volumes this is the same
as topologically the same as the Taurus
that's what I mean and similarly if you
have that REM surface of Gus G you can
draw it like this it's the same thing
the only important thing is how many of
those handles or those what I called
sort of places that you can hold you
have and you have G of these and you
have G of those okay good well an
exercise
then
let's imagine a surface like this
now I'm sorry that you have to draw many
pictures well actually I'm not sorry
that's what why you here for but can you
draw this picture very
fast it's going to be quite a
challenge I'll draw it and then explain
what it is what I'm drawing is
effectively a cube skeleton of a cube
but made from not wires but
tubes can you visualize
this I hope you can
visualize um easily how you make a cube
with just straight
wires straight um lines if you like now
imagine that you replace each line by a
tube and then make make something like
this okay so that's a surface it's a
surface in the sense that you know
inside there's a hollow space and I can
put for example milk in it and then just
shake shake shake shake and make make a
milkshake
and why did I mention milkshake maybe I
want milkshake but anyway so that's
surface closed surface there's no
boundary
question this surface turns out to be
one of Sigma G's which one is it how
many um holes or how many handles does
it have what is it what's its
genus which Sigma G is
this so I'd like to and take a vote on
this who thinks that it is Sigma 0 what
does sigma0 mean do you
remember S2 so it's a sphere do you
think it's just a
sphere no it looks more complicated than
sphere I hope yeah so it's not Sigma 0
who thinks it's Sigma
1 it's homeomorphic you think to a
single Taurus who thinks it's Sigma one
any
takers nobody's taking it's cheap Sig
and okay we'll get there who thinks is
Sigma 2 it's two copies of torai put
together ni connection who thinks it's
Sigma 2 who thinks it's Sigma 3 by the
way you you have to vote for one of
those you have to decide Sigma
3 Sigma 4 ah Sigma 4 good there some
take us Sigma 4 excellent and sigma 5
who thinks is Sigma
5 hey no what does Nas think Sigma 5
Sigma
6 ah six that's interesting because it
has six faces
prob huh is that why do you think yes
you didn't votee and you're saying did
you vote okay thank you very much Sigma
Sigma
7 Sigma
8 I said that everyone must vote which
means which means that everyone think
almost everyone thinks it's more than
Sigma
9 is that what you think I think you
should have voted a little
earlier
huh which one would you like to vote for
Sigma Sigma 6 you think okay now that's
a very good guess however appearances
can be misleading please imagine that
you look this picture from the top H
from the
top what would you see you see this
picture can you draw the picture of this
as you see it from the top
this is what you would
see do you
agree how many holes are there
five so it's not Sigma 6 although there
are six faces it's Sigma 5 interesting h
so appearances can be misleading but
also interesting
okay how about
this
eraser another
exercise I hope you enjoyed drawing that
picture in your notebooks but how about
this sorry
that is another surface and I'm going to
put
some holes in
there how about this can you imagine
what this is so this is kind of a tube
that goes around around it's a simple U
sorry single piece of surface and here I
put in a handle that I can hold so what
is which one which Sigma is this
huh okay let's take a vote who thinks
it's Sigma 0 of course it's not Sigma 0
how about Sigma 1 Sigma 2 Sigma 3 okay
Sigma 4 Sigma 5 Sigma 6 Sigma 7 Sigma 8
it turns out to be Sigma 4 but um I hope
I counted right okay anyway it's kind of
um curious but um that's what it is you
don't think it's Sigma huh
huh how do I know it's Sigma 4 because
the teacher said so
well how do you react to this huh you
should you know rise in Revolt and they
say no no no and then you have a
revolution um no you shouldn't say okay
how do I know
this first of all the fact that
something is
Tangled Up In Space really does not
matter okay what I mean is this let's
say that you have a tube a single tube
and suppose that I put the tube like
this it's still Sigma
one do you see it's a single oops what
am I doing something's wrong
here you see you should be drawing good
pictures as somebody says all the time I
mean
this okay so that's that's still Sigma
one I just put it in space and of course
inside space I cannot undo this not to
make it like that but that does not
affect the
genus it's the same surface okay
intrinsically and otherwise so this
noted doesn't matter so in particular
you can unnote these things I can take
this off take this off and what you
really have in the end is only this
surface do you see it's the same thing
and then 1 2 3 four panles and that's
Sigma 4 which one you huh which one
you
again yeah if I can undo the knots but
because the knottedness does not affect
does not has nothing to do with the
genus nness has to do with how you put
represent that surface in
space but genus has to do with something
more intrinsic more proper to the
surface than that this point is a little
difficult to explain and in fact how you
actually determine the genus Define the
genus is a more advanced but I hope that
I can rely on intuition to make forward
and make
progress
okay
now should I go there okay let's go
here let's go back to the real
projective plane you remember that
strange thing that we discussed in the
beginning
recall that the real projected plane is
made how do you
remember
rp2 the picture was
this is made by taking a sphere and with
a hole and gluing a movie strip on this
hole closing it with a lid which is in
the form of movie strip
okay on the
sphere
well in definition 16 we constructed we
considered the connected sum of lots of
copies of Tor let's
consider a connected sum of lots of
copies of rp2 of the re projected
plane R2 so what does it look
like for example you
can take
two copies of rp2 and make a connected
sign when you glue what you get
is something like
this this I hope you are following what
this picture means it's a rather
abstract sophisticated picture but we
are all sophisticated people what we do
is you take a sphere you take out two
holes two drill two holes and then put a
lid on each of those holes not with the
disc but with the mov that's what we do
and it's difficult to draw but that's
how it's represented in by
convention
okay definition um which is parallel to
that Sigma
G we shall consider a surface denoted by
n subg
actually because this is parallel to
Sigma this should be not the Roman
alphabet N but the Greek alphabet New
Capital new G but it doesn't matter
which one you
consider you take a
sphere and you put
G
leads of movie strip
on the
sphere before for Sigma G we had G
handles on the sphere here we have G
Lids on movie strip um BDS of movie
strip on a sphere and this is naturally
equal
to you can write the formula for this no
problem although it's difficult to
visualize it's lots of copies of
rp2 connect some with rp2 o oops
are
P2 and so on to
rp2 just as before we had connected some
of copies of
P2 unfortunately this surface has no
standard
name you might want want to amuse
yourself giving it the name for example
the the
surface okay oh n surface because this
is n anyway um that's the surface and we
shall note that as
before n0 by convention if you have an
empty summation is by convention you
guessed it's
S2 and you'll see why we are putting
these conventions because later when we
do the surg
S2s behave like zero so we want to
assign the zero value to this one and
also we
note that N1 is simply equal to a single
copy bar P2 just as
before
okay well we have now met two classes of
surfaces remember surfaces of genus G
Sigma GS and then nggs which don't have
names it turns out that the foral ones
Sigma G are orientable and the latter
ones and GES are non-orientable and that
is the full set of all the surfaces that
exist in the universe that theorem was
noticed and proved by Mr movus himself
you thought muis was some strange alien
from outer space but in fact he was a
professor mathematics in Germany why did
he have a such a strange name muus I
don't know but he worked in a large
number of areas including complex
analysis and you might have heard of
muus Transformations sometimes called
linear fractional Transformations the
French people call them homography but
anyway so that's the work by
mbius okay so the theorem is a
classification theorem and we shall not
prove this but it's good to know that
it's there first start theorem is that
Sigma Gs are all
orientable if you like two-
sided n gs are
nonorientable or new G is are
nonorientable that's why I call them new
because as in non non orientable
okay
also every two
dimensional compact
[Applause]
manifold also known in ordinary English
as surface without
[Applause]
boundary is homeomorphic to one of
them and only one of
[Applause]
them Sigma G or
new thus we have a full complete
classification of manif force in
dimension two
[Applause]
okay you might have met in the course of
your mathematical studies whatever your
former degree was physics chemistry
engineering computer science what have
you biology in mathematics you might
have met classification theorems so you
have some class of objects
that have certain that characterized by
some properties and you want to classify
all those objects for example
classification of all finite groups
classification of all Vector spaces they
are classified by Dimension very easy
classification or classification of all
the matrices a famous theorem is Jordan
canonical form classification of this
classification of that and you might
have heard also of the pankar conjecture
which was settled a few years ago
and that's part of the classification
attempt as well people wanted to
classify all threedimensional
manifolds here you see that already in
the 19th century all two dimensional
manifolds if you like two dimensional
geometric figures have been classified
we know all of them there's a complete
list one dimensional classification you
might wonder well there's only one
closed manifold in 1D it's just a circle
there's nothing else that's very nice
in 3D it took
until very recently so po conjecture was
really the last piece if you like or
what sort of symbolized the last piece
it's actually part of the larger program
called the geometrization conjecture
which is in many ways more important
than P itself but anyway classification
of geometric figures manifolds is a very
difficult problem
now two
remarks you might then think what about
4 four dimension and above it must be
terribly difficult to do 4D and above it
turns out that in five dimension and
above in a certain technical
sense up to homotopy equivalence all
manifolds have been
classified about um 40 years ago so five
dimension above was easier than
dimensions three and
four and you'll see in the rest of this
course that actually higher Di stations
get easier sometimes because they have
more room to move there's more
freedom Dimension four is very difficult
and it's still open we cannot classify
all manifolds in dimension four and
there are good reasons to believe that
it's beyond our capability for quite a
long time but 3D is more or less
finished in some very rough sense
okay okay good now um let's see a bit
more
examples so that we
can our
[Music]
ination according to that
theorem due to Mr muus or her
muus we should be able to identify any
closed surface closed means compact
without boundary in case you don't know
the word compact don't worry
and so all the surfaces that we have met
you know you remember the varet of
manifolds that I discussed before I
began the discussion today we should be
able to recognize them as one of the
sigma G's or one of the new G's n G's so
here is the first little quiz example
20 which one of the sigma G or n u
[Applause]
is a clim
botle well you have to remember what the
clim botle looks like or how it's
represented but it must be one of Sigma
G's or newu G's because it's a two
dimensional surface and we have a
complete classification so it must be
one of Sigma G is new G's but which one
is
it well first the clim bottle is
orientable or nonorientable
does it have an inside and outside do
you remember what the climb botle looks
like if you take a tube like this and
then close it normally you get a Taurus
and that's of course orientable because
there's an outside and inside but clim
bottle you take a tube and close it by
intersecting its own surface from the
inside it's a bit like the
two-dimensional version of a movie strip
and do you remember yesterday we showed
that if you slice the ciment bottle in
its plane of symmetry it splits into two
copies of the movie strip so cim bottle
contains a movie strip in in it
therefore it must be nonorientable movie
strip that has no has only one side so
it is non
reable so it is one
not the 's so that it's not the G
because all the sigma Gs are
orientable okay so which one is it
then
now let's start thinking this way let's
recall that if you take a mov strip and
then glue it to a disk
[Applause]
what do you
get thank you you get
rp2 we did that about 30 minutes ago
so if you
take a sphere or the sorry
rp2 and then take away a dis
minus dis what do you think this
is is a it must be
sorry if you put the movie um movie
strip on the dis you get rp2 so if you
take away a disc from to you
get you get the movie of course yeah
movus plus dis is rp2 rp2 minus dis is a
movus
okay ah so this is good news
because what do we get if I do
this those are two copies of that
picture rp2 minus dis rp2 minus dis and
then I glue
together those two boundaries you get
the connected
sum of two RP
[Applause]
2s
yeah yes but this is also muus plus muus
what is it it's a CL
so clim
bot
is and which
one two two copies of R2 so we now know
that clim bottle is indeed on that list
as hopefully we were
confident okay the fact that this is a
clim bottle I think was explained in
example 11 yesterday so that you can
make a reference
to backward in time
okay you see we are drawing lots of
pictures and in fact we are already
drawing lots and lots of sophisticated
pictures monsters in obscure parts of
the
universe but all those surfaces do exist
and are legal citizens of the world of
mathematics and they do appear in very
surprising
applications okay
another picture of clim
moto so we have now several pictures of
Cl b the original one and then as M2 in
other words the connected sum of rp2 and
rp2 and another picture of clim which
will often
[Applause]
use is as
follows is let's start with this rather
primitive version of the cim botle
picture of the clim botle yeah you can
see that it's a clot
you have a tube and then you cut across
itself and then glue it back to close
let's think of this in the following
manner I'm going to faten the
bottom and then I imagine this tube
which mysteriously goes
inside and then is about to connect and
there's a hole here so if I connect
these two things that's a
climbable okay but you see if I connect
it this way
you can picture the clim b in this
fashion do you know what I mean this
strange intersection is because we
cannot do it in 3D we have to cut across
its own membrane it's sort of made of
magic material but this part is exactly
as we explained when we visualize the
handle so you have a surface you have a
hole and then from this hole a cube
ising coming out okay this is also true
but the tube is connected the surface
from the inside rather than from the
outside yeah clim bottle being
nonorientable it started on the outside
but magically it can get into inside and
then connected from the inside so okay
if I put my finger in here I can go into
this tube yeah but here if I grab it I
cannot access what's inside you can see
so
inside and outside although the in fact
there's no inside outside and I can move
this slide over here so the end picture
that I shall often use we shall often
use in calculations with pictures is
this
representation that's a picture of the
clim tool that we will
use
huh no it's a clim tool is nonorientable
and it must be one of the NS and in fact
it's N2 yeah so clim bottle is N2 as we
discussed so this is also N2 it's a
picture of a clim an alternative picture
of a clim now this should look slightly
familiar indeed you see here what we
have is a handle that starts on the
outside and then somehow mysteriously
goes inside and then connects to the
surface from inside if I have a handle
which is more normally behaved starts
from the outside and connects to the
surface back on on the outside like this
as I called it something that you can
carry this is just a T2 it's a
Taurus so it's not Sigma 2 so that's
Sigma 2 but that's
N2 yeah
okay good so I think we have been
um working hard enough for quite a while
so we shall call it um the day for for
today